Guide to the Uganda Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Uganda collection
1896-2012
MS 1548
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.27
(11 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history and current political, economic, and social conditions in Uganda.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history and current political, economic, and social conditions in Uganda.
Arrangement
The material in the first accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Education -- Uganda; Human rights -- Uganda; Uganda -- Description and travel; Uganda -- Economic conditions; Uganda -- Politics and government; Uganda -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Uganda; Amin, Idi, 1925-2003; National Resistance Movement (Uganda)
- Inventory
  - [Kasagama, Dandi, Omukama of Toro?]: correspondence to unidentified recipient (written in [Luganda?]), 1896 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Amateka Ne Biragiro: Ebyatesebwa Olukiko Olukulu Okuva 1922-1923," Mengo Press, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Ebiragiro By'Olukiko Eby'entesa", 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Development of Local Government in Uganda: Provincial Councils Being Set Up," Colonial Office Press Section, 1948 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Budo School/United Budonian Club: constitution, correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Government of the Uganda Protectorate: reports, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Nsamizi Training Center: adult education course brochure, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Note on the Africanization of the Uganda Civil Services," by C. J. Hall, 1960 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Independence Anniversary": program of celebrations, 1964 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "The Constitution of the Uganda Soviet Friendship and Cultural Society", [1964?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Economy/banking: journals, magazines, newspapers, 1965-1969, 1981-1985, [1991?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Teacher: A Magazine of Current Ideas for Uganda Schools: National Institute of Education, Makerere University, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Department of Political Science/Philosophy, Makerere University: papers, reports, 1970, 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Makerere University: newspaper, literary arts journal, 1972, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Shocking Secret World of Idi Amin, Brutal Tyrant of Uganda," in Collectors Editions, [1976] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Democratic Party (DP): manifesto, printed materials, 1980, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - News magazines, 1980-1982, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newspapers, 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18 - 19)
  - Leadership: A Magazine for Christian Leaders in Africa, 1981 September (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - U. N. Mission in Uganda: general information, map, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - News bulletins/newsletters, 1982, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mkombozi: Uganda National Liberation Army Monthly, 1982 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Congress: Magazine of Uganda Peoples Congress, 1982 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Amnesty International: reports, memorandum, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Conservative Party, summarized objectives of, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Uganda Human Rights Activists (UHRA): pamphlets, booklets, briefs, [1985-1986?], undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Uganda Newsletter: publication of The Embassy of the Republic of Uganda (Washington, D. C.), 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mamdani, Mahmood, printed materials of the Committee for the Restoration of M. Mandani's Ugandan Citizenship (CRMUC), [1985?]-1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Freedom of the press/journalism, papers on, 1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "The New Uganda Newsletter": Bulletin of the Diplomatic and Foreign Relations Commission (D&F) and the Uganda National Liberation Front (Anti-Dictatorship)-UNLF(A-D), 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Peace-Maker: a journal published under the Peace Programme of Uganda - Food and Peace Project, 1987 May (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "The Armies of Uganda and Human Rights - A Personal Observation," by Roger P. Winter, director of the U. S. Committee for Refugees, 1987 July (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Museveni, Yoweri Kaguta: presidential address on the occasion of the 27th independence anniversary, 1989 October 9 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Programme for the Alleviation of Poverty and the Social Costs of Adjustment (PAPSCA), the Republic of Uganda, 1989 October (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The 6th of February: The Magazine of the National Resistance Army (NRA), 1989 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Centre for Basic Research (CBR): papers, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - National Resistance Movement (NRM): booklets, [1990?], undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Constitutional change, papers on the subject of, [1991], undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Foundation for African Development (FAD): conference papers and lectures, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Second Advisory Committee Meeting of the Global Coalition for Africa (GCA): papers, addresses, releases, 1992 May 8-9 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Human rights, papers on subject of, 1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Ebyaffe: an Exposition of Kabakaship and its Relationship to the Government of Uganda", 1993 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "The Economics of Agricultural Production II: A Small Scale Farming," by unidentified author, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - The Pearl! - Makula, by Enoch E. K. Mulira, Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Photographs, [1910?] (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Colonial life: stereoscopic photographs (Box 3)
    General
    See: Kenya Collection, Manuscript Group Number 1523, box 3, folder 30
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-204
  - Additional printed materials, 1970, 1988-1997, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-025
  - Additional printed materials, 1910, 1921-1964, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-039
  - Additional printed materials, 1987-1990, 1997, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-039
  - Electoral Commission pamphlet re referendum, 2000 Jun/July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The New Uganda Newsletter: Bulletin of the Diplomatic and Foreign Relations Commission (D&F) and Uganda National Liberation Front (Anti-Dictatorship)-UNFL (A-D), 1984 March-April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Resistance, published by the National Resistance Movement (NRM), vol.1, no. 1, 1989 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Uganda Land Alliance
    - "Customary Land Holding in Uganda", [1998] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The NGO Perspective on the Land Bill", 1998 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Report on Kibale Land Titles Research", 1997 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1981-2006; Accession 2010-M-081
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged as received.
  - The Bull Roasters (a sister paper of the Mitchellite), Makerere University, 1983 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Stage (a magazine for and about the performing arts in Uganda and abroad), 1986 December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Spider, Newsletter of the African Association for Literacy and Adult Education, 1992 March (Box 1)
  - Guild Bulletin: a weekly publication of Makerere Student's Guild, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Analysis, 1986 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kondomu (condom) sex education pamphlet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Activist, Uganda Human Rights Activists, 1987 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The People's Struggle (special supplement), 1987 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Economy, 1987 November-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Uganda Point, 1986 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Munnansi News Bulletin, 1982 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ngabo, 1981 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Etoil Yok (Karimojong Newspaper), 1982 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Citizen, 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Government Intervention in the Development of the Shelter Sector," (Ministry of Planning and Economic Development, Uganda), 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Paper presented at Conference on Shelter and Economic Development.
  - Uganda Facts and Figures - Uganda Bureau of Statistics, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The AIDS Support Organization (TASO) - Information Booklet, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manifesto of the National Resistance Movement (NRM), 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sunday Monitor, 2005 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The official results by polling stations of the 2006 presidential election - Daily Monitor, 2006 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Uganda Association of University Women: Bulletin, 1988 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conference on Shelter and Economic Development (Human Settlements, Environment and Development Collaborative), 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The 6th February: The People's Army Magazine, 1977 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poster: Vote Yoweri K. Museveni, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional material, 1927?-2012; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1927?-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Circa 2000-2012 (Folder 3, Box 2, Folder 1)